Luca Tironi

Executive Engineer

Luca Tironi

Chodowieckistrasse 33 10405 Berlin, DE

(+49) 1578 4290922 luca.tironi@gmail.com

Skills

As a **Manager** I am focused on building collaborative environments to foster excellence in product creation and innovation. I have scaled engineering teams and supported the company to acquire and retain the best talent. I organized the teams to be Agile, self-running and self-organizing.

As a **Technical Leader** I believe in the power of communication and problem solving. I have built both simple and complex systems from the ground up. I also led refactoring of legacy applications and structured methodologies to maintain and expand complex architectures.

As an **Engineer** I write tested, maintainable and efficient code. I can work from the front-end layer (CSS, HTML, JS) to the depths of the backend (Ruby, Go, C++, Microservices, API) and I have experience in DevOps as well (Docker, Cloud, Scaling, CI/CD).

As an **Entrepreneur** I want to use my technical perspective together with my business experience to create new and compelling products.

Experience

Native Instruments GmbH / Engineering Manager

January 2018 - Present (2 years, 1 month), Berlin

I am responsible for ~30 engineers in the 6 teams behind products like Kontakt, Reaktor, several beloved NI synths like Massive, FM8, Absynth and newly released Massive X. Without forgetting Guitar Rig and all the effects bundles such as Crush and Mod Pack.

As an Engineering Manager, I take care of people as a servant leader. I support their professional development and empower the teams by guiding, coaching and encouraging natural leadership.

I am also the hiring manager and I am responsible to retain the top talents. I identify gaps and foster synergies, facilitating collaboration, communication and decision making within and between the teams.

DaWanda GmbH / Head of Engineering

May 2016 - December 2017 (1 year, 8 months), Berlin

I managed 35+ engineers and structured them in product teams as full-stack units, in order to maintain and grow the DaWanda Marketplace Platform. I recruited new engineers to scale the Engineering Team. I developed a process together with the Engineering Leads to create a Technical Vision and grow a healthy Engineering Culture.

I represented the engineering perspective across the company and contributed to strategic decisions according to the Technical Vision. I established a process to foster personal and professional development of engineers through timely and open feedback. I improved the Agile product management methodologies and introduced the OKRs to the Product Engineering Department.

DaWanda GmbH / Team Lead Software Development

November 2014 - April 2016 (1 year, 6 months), Berlin

I led the "Buyers" cross-functional team (7 people) in expanding and improving the DaWanda Marketplace Platform. I contributed to the design and developed the first iterations of the DaWanda Mobile Apps.

As the Engineering Hiring Manager I improved the recruiting process and scaled the team consistently. I developed the foundation of the Backend API that powered the mobile apps and the frontend.

UALA Srl / CTO & Co-Founder

June 2013 - October 2015 (2 years, 4 months), Milan

I co-founded and bootstrapped a new company in Milan called UALA: a marketplace for hundreds of hairstylists, beauty salons, SPAs and aesthetic centers all across Italy.

I developed the first iteration of the web marketplace, the administrative backoffice and the API for the tablet and mobile apps. I formed and trained the development team (4 people) and built the infrastructure for the continuous delivery of the platform.

DaWanda GmbH / Frontend Developer

August 2013 - October 2014 (1 year, 2 months), Berlin

I joined as a frontend/fullstack developer in an agile international Product Development team. Together we built and maintained the biggest German Marketplace dedicated to Handmade and DIY products.

I helped the Product Development team to maintain and improve our multi-service platform, coding mainly in Ruby (on Rails), Javascript and other cutting-edge web technologies.

Fractalgarden Srl / Senior Developer, Product Designer

May 2011 - July 2013 (2 years, 3 months), Milan

Business Analysis and Development of new products. UX and Frontend Development with Ruby on Rails.

I curated the development of an IoT Photovoltaic Monitoring Platform dedicated to O&M companies and Solar Investments Funds. I was also responsible for the UX and interface design. I developed the iOS companion Mobile App for the platform and managed several refactorings of the platform's architecture and interface.

I developed and contributed to several other projects like custom E-Commerce Platforms and ERP Systems.

Università Bocconi / Expert Fellow

January 2010 - July 2010 (7 months), Milan

I collaborated in the design of the course "Managing in the 2.0 Landscape", part of the EMIT english course at Bocconi University (MSc, first year). I taught about topics such as social media tools' impacts in the work environment, web entrepreneurship and web application design and development.

I tutored 15 groups of students in their group-works: the development of a Business Plan in the Web 2.0 and Social Media environment.

SDA Bocconi School of Management / Senior Developer

September 2007 - March 2011 (3 years, 6 months), Milan

I designed and developed several business games and simulations, used in MBAs, masters and executives courses and other tools to support learning and teaching in education programs.

I researched the Web 2.0 phenomenon, designed and delivered lectures to students with in depth analysis of the growing importance of new media and their social, economic and technological impacts.

Freelancer / Web Developer

January 2006 - December 2007 (2 years), Bergamo

I designed and developed several websites and applications for italian companies and institutions, such as the Ministry of Public Education.

Education

Università degli Studi di Milano / BSc in Computer Science

2002 - 2006, Milan

Thesis: Realtime Terrain Rendering: optimization methods and techniques

The course of study was focused on general and graphic programming, game development, AI and communication through digital media.

Liceo Classico Statale Paolo Sarpi / High School Diploma

1997 - 2002, Bergamo

Humanistic studies, Philosophy, Art, Latin and Ancient Greek.

Personal Projects

My Pretty Milano / iPhone & Android App

In 2011 I developed and launched an iPhone/Android app that featured cool venues and events in my city (Milano) with reviews and recommendations, collected by a small team of fashion victims and illustrated by a designer.

The apps have been downloaded more than 6600 times and had 3000+ active users.

lucatironi.net / Personal website

A site to share some of the knowledge and the code that I accumulated during my coding experience.

Technology Skills

Frontend Web Development: HTML, CSS, JavaScript (Angular, React)

Backend Web Development/DevOps: Ruby (on Rails), GoLang, monolith and MicroService Architecture

Mobile Development: Android and iOS, Progressive WebApps

General Coding: C++, Scripting, Unix

Others: DevOps experience, AWS, GCP, Heroku, Docker

Others

Languages: Fully proficient in English. Native Italian and basic German.

Hobbies: Cinema, Music Production, DIY, Sailing